Guide to the Lin Carter Papers, 1900s-2001 and undated RL.11079
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lin Carter papers
1900s-2001 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carter, Lin, 1930-1988
RL.11079
12 Linear Feet
Lin Carter (1930-1988, aka H. P. Lowcraft, Grail Undwin) was an American author of science fiction and fantasy, editor, poet and critic. The Lin Carter Papers span the years 1900 to 2001 and consist mainly of documents stemming from Carter's own work as a writer and editor, other authors' manuscripts sent to Carter, unidentified writings likely being written by Carter, and personal and professional correspondence addressed to Carter (e.g. with Sprague de Camp, Roy A. Squires, et al.).
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into series: Writings, Correspondence, Notes and Materials, and Personal Documents.
Biographical / Historical
Linwood Vrooman Carter (June 9, 1930–February 7, 1988) was an American author of science fiction and fantasy, as well as an editor, poet and critic. He usually wrote as Lin Carter; known pseudonyms include H. P. Lowcraft (for an H. P. Lovecraft parody) and Grail Undwin. He is best known for editing the Ballantine Adult Fantasy series in the 1970s, which introduced readers to many overlooked classics of the fantasy genre. Carter was born in St. Petersburg, Florida. He was an avid reader of science fiction and fantasy in his youth and became broadly knowledgeable in the field. He was also quite active in fandom. Carter served in the United States Army (Infantry, Korea, 1951–53), after which he attended Columbia University (1953–54), during which time he attended Leonie Adams's Poetry Workshop. He was a copywriter for some years before writing full-time. He married twice, first to Judith Ellen Hershkovitz (married 1959; divorced 1960) and later to Noel Vreeland (married 1963, while they both worked for Prentice-Hall publishers; divorced 1975). He was an advertising and publishers copywriter (1957–69). From 1969 he was a freelance writer and editorial consultant. During much of his writing career he lived in Hollis, New York. He was a member of the all-male literary banqueting club the Trap Door Spiders, which served as the basis of Isaac Asimov's fictional group of mystery solvers the Black Widowers. Carter himself was the model for the Mario Gonzalo character. He was also a member of the Swordsmen and Sorcerers' Guild of America (SAGA), a loose-knit group of Heroic fantasy authors founded in the 1960s, some of whose work he anthologized in the Flashing Swords! series. In the 1970s Carter issued his own fantasy fanzine, titled Kadath, after H. P. Lovecraft's fictional setting. In 1985, he developed oral cancer leading to his death in 1988. He resided in East Orange, New Jersey in his final years, and died in nearby Montclair, New Jersey.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Lin Carter Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from John Betancourt in 2015.
Collection Overview
The Lin Carter Papers span the years 1900 to 2001 and consist mainly of documents stemming from Carter's own work as a writer and editor, other authors' manuscripts sent to Carter, unidentified writings likely being written by Carter, and personal and professional correspondence addressed to Carter (e.g. with Sprague de Camp, Roy A. Squires, et al.). Included also are some legal, financial, and other official documents (e.g. Carter's first divorce and army papers, agreements with publishers, etc.), personal photographs, and some personal artifacts (wallet with ID cards, name tag of the Brotherhood of Jedi Knights, etc.). Materials on Carter's own writings include manuscripts, typescripts, notes and notebooks as well as clipped articles, sketches and other materials (e.g. with regard to the Thongor, Eric Carstairs of Zanthodon, Callisto, and Conan series; Atlantis trilogy, Wizard of Oz writings, "posthumous collaborations" on Robert E. Howard's Conan the Barbarian, Clark Ashton Smith's Book of Eibon, and H. P. Lovecraft's Cthulhu Mythos and Necronomicon, planned writings and anthologies, etc.). Papers with regard to Carter's work as an editor include manuscripts, typescripts, notes, and correspondence with regard to Weird Tales, Bellantine Adult Fantasy series, Flashing Swords!, The Year's Best Fantasy Stories, Carter's Clark Ashton Smith Biography, and his research on H. P. Lovecraft (including copies and transcripts of letters, manuscripts, and official documents by the latter two). Some papers refer to Carter's memberships in the literary club the Trap Door Spiders, the Swordsmen and Sorcerers' Guild of America (SAGA), The New Kalem Club, and the International Wizard of Oz Club. Most of the materials are in very good condition. Some of Carter's published works included in this collection are reprints by Wildside Press, dating to the 1990s and 2000s. Some pages of paper typescripts might be fragile.
Authors, American -- 20th century; Fan magazines; Fiction -- 20th century; Periodical editors; Weird tales; Science fiction -- Authorship; Speculative fiction; Smith, Clark Ashton, 1893-1961; Howard, Robert E. (Robert Ervin), 1906-1936; Lovecraft, H. P. (Howard Phillips), 1890-1937; Wildside Press; Betancourt, John
- Writings, 1900s-1990 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  ..
  - Carter's Writings, 1
    - A is for Aardvark (edited by Lin Carter), undated (Box 11)
    - About the Slayer of Souls and Robert W. Chambers: Lord of the Black Throne, 1980 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, copyright 1980; originally included in one folder with "The High History of Sinbad the Sailor" and "Lost Races, Forgotten Cities" with attached note "For Amra or Amazing"
    - Acolyte of the Flame. A Translation of Fragment MXI of the Pnakotic Manuscripts, undated (Box 1)
      typescript
    - The Adventures of Thad Dexter on the Red Planet: A Swordsman of Mars, undated (Box 9)
      Draft
    - The Avenger of Carthage, undated (Box 1)
      notes and second typescript draft with handwritten notes of "The Burning City"
    - After the Moon Fell, undated (Box 9)
      Typed draft
    - After the Moon Fell/The Enchantress of World's End, undated (Box 1)
      typescripts and notes
    - Amadis of Gaul, undated (Box 1)
      notes
    - Amalric, undated (Box 9)
      Draft with Carter's title page
    - Amra articles, undated (Box 1)
      includes typescripts of "In Defense of Heroes," "J. Allen St. John. A Tribute," "Swordmen of Vistar by Charles Nuetzel," "A Voyage to Atlantis by James W. Mavor," untitled (on Atlantis)
    - Ancient Rome and co, undated (Box 1)
      notes and clippings
    - The Ancient Wisdom, undated (Box 9)
      Notes
    - And Whether Pigs Have Wings (Introduction)/Return to Jabberwock (1987)/The Yonghy-Bonghy-Bo Revisited (1987) from unidentified anthology ed. By Carter, 1987 and undated (Box 1)
      complete typescript with handwritten notes of Carter's introduction, "Return to Jabberwock" (1987), and "The Yonghy-Bonghy-Bo Revisited" (1987); also including the texts by the other others in the anthology (incl. texts by Ogden Nash, Hilaire Belloc, William Jay Smith, Walter de la Mare, J. R. R. Tolkien, C. S. Lewis, T. H. White, John Gardner, Mervyn Peake, Richard Adams, Palmer Brown, Nancy Byrd Turner, Dr. Seuss, Spike Milligan, Edward Gorey, Christopher Isherwood, A. A. Milne, Jack Prelutsky, Roger Lancelyn Green, Edward Abbott Parry, and James Thurber)
    - The Archives of Pelaire: A Saul Everest Adventure, undated (Box 9)
    - Art Magick, undated (Box 1)
      miscellaneous notes on magic and mysticism throughout history
    - At the Sign of the Centaur, 1950 Feb. (Box 1)
      typescript from early Feb. 1950
    - Atlantis Trilogy (Vol. 1: The White Throne), undated (Box 1)
      includes two typescript versions of a "Synopsis" and typescript with handwritten notes of "The White Throne," manuscript of an "Introduction" to "The "White Throne," a typescript "Appendix. Is the Atlantis Legend True?", various notes on (Star of) Atlantis/Azphar the Evil Star/Black Star (incl. typescript with notes on "The City of the Golden Gates, according to Critias," Plato et al., and handdrawn map of Atlantis, "Vandar of Lemuria, Prince of the Last Days")
    - Atlantis Trilogy (Vol. 2: The Black Star, unpublished (?)), undated (Box 1)
      includes incomplete typescripts of "Black Star," incl. pp. 13-18 with "1. Herpes Zoster. i. Borochan the Jewel-Merchant, ii. Crysarion of Ith," continued with attached note "Carbon of old version" incl. pp.19-43 with 1.iii to 1.v., "2. Phaona of Adalon," and "3. The Golden Wyvern," "Prologue. The Hour of the Vulture" with attached note "Carbon of new version," two more typescripts of "Prologue: The Hour fo the Vulture," "The Prologue to The Black Star," and "The Story of the Black Star"
    - Baleful Myths and Liturgies: Clark Ashton Smith's Contributions to the Cthulhu Mythos, undated (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes
    - Banner with a Strange Deuice, undated (Box 9)
      Original carbon
    - Behind the Mask (Cthulhu Mythos), 1980 May (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original manuscript of this Cthulhu mythos tale, written in May, 1980"
    - The Bell in the Tower, undated (Box 1)
    - The Benevolence of Yib (Simrana Tale), 1979 Sept. 16 (Box 1)
      typescript, incl. note "Only existing manuscript of this Simrana tale, written in its entirety on September 16, 1979"
    - Beyond the Worlds We Know (Part I), undated (Box 1)
    - Beyond the Worlds We Know (Part II: Star Pirate Discovers the Astounding Secret of the Mystery Planet), undated (Box 1)
    - Black Cone of Nith; Hour of the Unseen Howling. A Response by Lin Carter, undated (Box 1)
    - Black Hawk of Valkarth, 1973 Jan. 10 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original manuscript of the Thongor 'origin' story, completed on 10 Jan., 1973"
    - Black Pearl o' Tortuga, undated (Box 9)
    - The Black Star, 1973 (Box 11)
      Lin Carter Discovery Series, Wildside Press edition, 1999.
    - Black Stars in the Skull of Doom. NOT by Robert E. Howard, 1988 (Box 1)
      typescript with some handwritten notes
    - Black Water, ed. by Alberto Manguel (Clarkson N. Potter: 1983), reviewed by Carter, undated (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes of review by Carter
    - The Book of Eibon: general notes, undated (Box 1)
      type- and manuscripts with general notes on "The Book of Eibon" and tables of contents
    - The Book of Eibon: History and Chronology (Charnel House Chapbooks), undated (Box 1)
      typescript and proofs
    - The Book of Eibon: In the Vale of Pnath, undated (Box 1)
      two typescript versions
    - The Book of Eibon: Papyrus of the Dark Wisdom (Book 3), undated (Box 1)
      two typescript versions with handwritten notes, incl. the chapters "The Unbegotten Source" (i), "The Polar Ones" (ii), "The Elder Beings" (iii), "The Great Race of Yith" (iv), "The City of the Archives" (v), "The Coming of Cthulhu"
    - The Book of Eibon: The Double Tower, 1973 Jun. 24 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "This is the only original copy of the final version of the second collaboration, completed 24 June 1973"
    - The Book of Eibon: The Light From the Pole, 1975 Dec. (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. "only original manuscript of this fifth of the posthumous collaborations from 'The Book of Eibon,' completed December 2, 1975"
    - The Book of Eibon: The Scroll of Morloc, 1973 Dec. 21 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original manuscript of this third of the post-humous collaborations from 'The Book of Eibon,' completed December 21, 1973"
    - The Book of Eibon: The Secret in the Parchment, 1981 Jan. 23 and undated (Box 1)
      manuscript; typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original manuscript of this tale from 'The Book of Eibon,' completed January 23, 1981."
    - The Book of Eibon: The Stairs in the Crypt, 1974 Oct. and undated (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original manuscript copy of this fourth of the posthumous collaborations from 'The Book of Eibon,' completed October 7, 1974"; manuscript of draft I; typescript of 3rd version with note "completed Oct 6 '74"
    - The Book of Eibon: The Utmost Abomination, 1973 Jan. 31 (Box 1)
      notes, typescripts with handwritten notes of the first and second draft, typescript of another version with handwritten notes, incl. note "This third and final draft of the first in the series of posthumusly (sic) collaborative translations from 'The Book of Eibon' was completed on 31 January 1973, and this is the only original copy of the final version"
    - The Book of Eibon: untitled (Pharazyn the prophet), undated (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incomplete, likely fragment of "The Light From the Pole: History of Pharazyn the Prophet"
    - A Bottle of Djinn Sweet Tooth, undated (Box 9)
    - Bronze Age Novel, undated (Box 1)
    - Bullseye. A Sam Jones of the Sentinel Mystery, undated (Box 1)
    - Caliban, undated (Box 9)
      Drafts
    - Cerberus the Irrumator, 1986 Jun. 14 (Box 9)
      Manuscript draft
    - Chaldean Mysteries: The Secret Laws Behind Magic, undated (Box 9)
      Notes and drafts
    - The Champeen Hornswogglers of Squaw Poker Flats, 1975 and undated (Box 1)
      four typescript versions with handwritten notes, one dated 1975
    - Chronicles of the Sword 1-4 ("Kingdoms of the Dawn," "The First Barbarian," "Out of Cimmeria," "The Kind is Dead"), 1974 (Box 1)
      notes and typescripts with handwritten notes and dates on title pages: "Written 12 May 1974; only original copy" ("Kingdoms of the Dawn"), "Written 12 May 1974; only original copy" ("The First Barbarian"), "Written August 22, 1974. Only original copy" ("Out of Cimmeria"), "Completed 25 Aug 1974. Only original copy" ("The Kind is Dead")
    - The City in the Jewel, 1972 Nov. 1 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Completed Nov. 1, 1972. Only original copy"
    - The City Outside of the World, undated (Box 1)
      notes and clippigns
    - The Clever Miller and the Gullible Ogre. Retold From an Old French Folktale, undated (Box 1)
    - Corsairs of the Cosmos, Star Pirate battles 'the Blur' in--. Can the Daredevil of the Spaceways Solve the Secret of the Invisible Mastermind of Crime?, undated (Box 1)
      two typescript versions with handwritten notes
    - Creating a Fantasy Hero. An Artille, 1974 Aug. 6 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original copy of the final manuscript written in its entirety on 6 Aug '74"
    - Crom of the Northlands, undated (Box 1)
      notes and title page
    - Cthulhu Mythos, undated (Box 1)
      incl. "A (Complete) Bibliography of the Cthulhu Mythos" in three versions, notes, an undated letter by Brian Lumley to Tom Collins re the publication of Cthulhu mythos tales, a typescript of the poem "The History of Science" by W. H. Auden, a copy of "The Brain-Eaters" by Frank Belknap Long
    - Curse of the Black Pharao, undated (Box 1)
      incomplete typescript (pp. 22-26, 28-111, end)
    - Curse of the Black Pharaoh, undated (Box 9)
    - Damis the Apollonian, 1986 May 7 and undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Manuscript draft and notes
    - Darya of the Bronze Age: The Adventures of Eric Carstairs in Zanthodon, 1981 (Box 11)
      Daw Books paperback edition
    - Dead of Night, undated (Box 9)
    - Death-Song of Conan the Cimmerian, 1972 Aug. (Box 1)
      typescript with the note "Composed in Detroit, August 1972. The original manuscript" and "The original notes"
    - The Descent into the Abyss, undated (Box 1)
      incomplete manuscript and typescript with handwritten notes
    - The Desolation Beyond Death, undated (Box 1)
      typescript with extensive handwritten notes, draft 2
    - The Devil Tree, undated (Box 1)
    - Digging up Atlantis, 1972 Dec. (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. the note "Only original manuscript December, 1972."
    - Dildae the Gorgon, 1986 May 14 (Box 9)
    - Double Trouble in Dorking, undated (Box 9)
    - Down There, undated (Box 9)
    - Down to a Sunless Sea, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Dreams From R'Lyeh: A Sonnet Cycle (incl. probably other poems), 1956-1970 and undated (Box 1)
      also incl. a manuscript with an English translation of "Bal des pendus" by Honore Balzac
    - Dreams in the House of Weir, 1979 Dec. 3 (Box 1)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only original manuscript of this Cthulhu mythos story completed 3 Dec. 1979, published in Weird Tales #1"
    - Duel of Wizards, undated (Box 9)
    - The Earth Shaker, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
      typescript (setting copy) with handwritten notes, foundry proofs
    - The Earth-Shaker: Zarkon 4, undated (Box 9)
      Assorted poems, excerpts
    - Ecronomicon, undated (Box 2)
      notes, correspondence, clippings
    - Elak of Atlantis, undated (Box 2)
      typescripts with handwritten notes in several drafts, notes, clippings
    - Eric Carstairs of Zanthodon, Vol. 4: Darya of the Bronze Age, undated (Box 2)
      typescript with handwritten notes (incl. Book I: "Princess in Peril," Book II: "Pirates of Zanthodon," Book III: "Conquerors of El-Cazar," Part IV: "The Hunters and the Hunted," Part V: "Blades of the Brotherhood," Part VI: "Battle Beneath the World"), pp. 8-9 missing
    - Eric Carstairs of Zanthodon, Vol. 5: Eric of Zanthodon, undated (Box 2)
    - Eric of Zanthodon, 1982 (Box 11)
    - Event flyers of events related to Carter, undated (Box 5)
      flyers for events with/related to Carter and his work
    - Fabulous Lives, undated (Box 2)
      type- and manuscripts in several drafts, notes
    - Fanzine articles, undated (Box 2)
      includes typescripts of "An Embattled 'Alice.' Jonathan Miller's Controversial Version of Lewis Carroll's Classic for Britsh Television is More 'Dali-land' than 'Disneyland'", "J. Allen St. John. A Tribute," "A Day in Derleth Country," "Discovered: A Link Between Cabell and Tolkien"
    - Father of Slime, undated (Box 2)
      typescripts with handwritten notes, notes
    - The Feaster From the Starts, undated (Box 2)
    - Final Curtain, undated (Box 2)
      manuscript
    - The Fishers From Outside, undated (Box 2)
    - The Flowers of Eros (first book), undated (Box 2)
    - For the Blood is the Life, undated (Box 2)
    - From the Archive of the Moon, 1986 May 20 (Box 2)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. note "Only existing original manuscript of this story, completed 20 May 1986
    - Future Collections and Anthologies, undated (Box 2)
    - Galactic Veebelfetzer, undated (Box 2)
    - Geydelle's Protective, undated (Box 2)
    - The Ghost-Chasers, undated (Box 2)
      incl. notes with ideas for anthologies with text by writes considered to be "ghost-chasers," typescript of "The Introduction. Meet the Ghost-Chasers," typescript of Carter's "Editor's Note" for the publication of "From the Casebook of John Silence. A Psychical Invasion" (1908) by Algernon Blackwood with copy Blackwood's story, typescript of Carter's "Editor's Note" for the publication of "The Haunter of the Ring" (1934) by Robert E. Howard with copy of Howard's story, typescript of "Editor's Note" for the publication of "From the Casebook of Carnacki. The Whistling Room" (1910) by William Hope Hodgson with copy of Hodgson's story, typescript of Carter's "Editor's Note" for the publication of "From the Casebook of Doctor Anton Zarnak. Curse of the Black Pharao" (1962) by Lin Carter
    - Ghosts of Ganymede, Star Pirate fights a phantom killer, in--, undated (Box 2)
    - Gilgamesh, 1969 Dec. 4 and undated (Box 2)
      type- and manuscript (several drafts, probably incomplete), letter by L. Sprague de Camp to Carter dated 12/04/1969
    - The Goblinry of Ais, undated (Box 2)
      typescript pp. 1-4, incomplete
    - The Gondwane Epic, undated (Box 9)
      Typescript, notes, edits. Includes Giant of World's End and The Warrior of World's End.
    - The Gondwane Epic book 2: The Enchantress of World's End, 1975, 2001 (Box 11)
      Wildside Press paperback edition, 2001.
    - The Gondwane Epic book 3: The Immortal of World's End, 1976, 2001
    - The Gondwane Epic book 5: The Pirate of World's End, 1978, 2001 (Box 11)
    - A Guide to the City, undated (Box 2)
    - Have Time, Will Travel: The Time-Travel School of Science Fiction, undated (Box 2)
    - He, undated (Box 2)
    - The High History of Sinbad the Sailor, 1975 Mar. 27 (Box 2)
      typescript with handwritten notes, incl. "Only original manuscript copy of the essay, which was completed 27 March 1975." and "For Amra or Amazing." Originally, the folder also included "About the Slayer of Souls and Robert W. Chambers: Lord of the Black Throne" and "Lost Races, Forgotten Cities."
    - The Higher Heresies of Oolimar, undated (Box 2)
      typescript of synopsis with handwritten notes
    - History of the Great Imperium, undated (Box 9)
      Includes Rogue Star and Mischief Maker drafts
    - Holmstead, undated (Box 2)
    - The Horn of the Unicorn, undated (Box 2)
      typescripts of two drafts with handwritten notes including "sample chapters and an outline of a fantasy novel for older children"
    - Horror Wears Blue, 1987 (Box 2)
      typescript and two versions of galley proofs (1987) with handwritten notes
    - Houssain, 1986 May 23 (Box 9)
    - How Ghuth Would Have Hunted the Slith, undated (Box 2)
      mansucript and typescript with handwritten notes
    - How Her Doom Came Down at Last on Adrazoon, 1987 Oct. 11 (Box 2)
      manuscript, dated 11 October 1987
    - The Hoy, undated (Box 2)
    - Hurok of the Stone Age: The Adventures of Eric Carstairs in Zanthodon, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Ikranos Series, undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
      Drafts of multiple short stories, etc.
    - Imaginary Worlds, 1970-1975 and undated (Box 2)
      notes (incl. "Data on Authors" consisting of article copies and clippings, and correspondence on Tolkien, Lovecraft, C. S. Lewis, Hannes Bok, Henry Rider Haggard, L. Sprague de Camp, et al.), reader responses to "Imaginary Worlds," copy of the magazine "nightshade," issue no. 1, and typescripts of texts by Carter (incomplete introduction on Ed Morrell (1971), "About Fantastic Traveller and Maude Meagher: Dome of Many-Colored Glass" (1972), "About the Star Rover and Jack London: Beyond the Body" (incomplete), "About The Devil's Own Dear Son, and James Branch Cabell: The Green Stone" (1972), "About The Roots of the Mountains and William Morris: The World-Maker" (1972), "About Thais, and Anatole France: Saint and Sinner" (1972), "About Zadig, and Other Miracles, and Voltaire: The Last Laugh" (undated), "About The Crock of Gold and James Stephens: The Treasure at Rainbow's End" (1972), "About When the World Shook and H. Rider Haggard: A South Seas Atlantis" (1974), "About the Revolt of the Angels and Anatole France: The Perils of Reading Too Much" (1971), "About the Elder Gods and John W. Campbell: Against the Invisible Ones" (1971)
    - The Intelligent Child's Own Book of Interesting and Instructive Monsters, undated (Box 9)
      Drafts, notes
    - Interview of F. C. Adams with Lin Carter on July 25 1973, undated (Box 2)
      typescripts with questions and text of the interview, incl. note "only original copy"
    - Into the Vortex. Adventures in the World Beyond the World, 1985 (Box 3)
    - The Island in the Sky, undated (Box 3)
    - Ivory and Orichalc and Jade. The Tales of Clark Ashton Smith. A Chronological Bibliography by Lin Carter, 1974 and undated (Box 3)
      type- and manuscript, notes
    - Journey to the Underground World: The Adventures of Eric Carstairs in Zanthodon, 1979 (Box 11)